A Finding Aid to the Fritz Bultman Papers, 1928-2010, bulk 1940s-1990s, in the Archives of American Art AAA.bultfrit
Archives of American Art
Fritz Bultman papers
1928-2010, bulk 1940s-1990s
AAA.bultfrit
Archives of American Art
9.2 Linear feet
The papers of New York School painter and sculptor Fritz Bultman, 1928-2010, bulk 1940s-1990s, measure 9.2 linear feet. They document Bultman's professional activities, ties to the Abstract Expressionist movement, and his personal life. Letters from friends and family include many from Hans and Maria Hofmann. Letters by Bultman are mostly to family; also found are a few drafts and copies of business and personal letters. Writings and notes are by and about Bultman. Notebooks/sketchbooks (39 volumes) include autobiographical writings, notes on dreams and thoughts while in psychoanalysis, many sketches and some completed drawings. Subject files reflect Bultman's professional activities, interests, and relationships; Hans Hofmann is the most thoroughly documented subject. Extensive printed material concerns Bultman's activities and exhibitions; also included are his published writings. Most photographs are of artwork, Bultman, his family and friends. Also found are biographical materials, 4 diaries, 6 interviews with Fritz Bultman and Jeanne Bultman, and a small amount of artwork.
Bultman, Fritz
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Gift of Fritz Bultman in 1984, with additions donated by Jeanne Bultman, his widow, in 1988 and 2000, and by his sons, Anthony F. Bultman, IV and Ellis Johann Bultman, in 2013.
Existence and Location of Copies note
Portions of this collection are available on 35 mm microfilm reels N70-40 and 60-61 and for interlibrary loan. Researchers should note that the arrangement of the papers as described in this finding aid may not reflect the order of the collection on microfilm due to reprocessing.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged in 10 series:
Series 1: Biographical Materials,1928-2003 (Box 1; 0.1 linear feet)
Series 2: Letters, 1930-1995 (Box 1; 0.4 linear feet)
Series 3: Interviews, 1968-1998 (Box 1; 0.4 linear feet)
Series 4: Writings and Notes, 1935-circa 1980s (Boxes 1-2; 0.8 linear feet)
Series 5: Notebooks/Sketchbooks, 1937-circa 1979 (Boxes 2-3, 11; 0.7 linear feet)
Series 6: Diaries, 1977-1979 (Box 3; 0.3 linear feet)
Series 7: Subject Files, 1942-2010 (Boxes 3-5, 11; 2.3 linear feet)
Series 8: Printed Material, 1941-2006 (Boxes 5-9, OV 12; 3.5 linear feet)
Series 9: Artwork, circa 1930s-1956 (Boxes 9, 11; 0.1 linear feet)
Series 10: Photographs, 1935-1997 (Boxes 9-10; 0.6 linear feet)
Scope and Contents note
The papers of New York School painter and sculptor Fritz Bultlman, 1928-2010, bulk 1940s-1990s, measure 9.2 linear feet. They document Bultman's professional activities, ties to the Abstract Expressionist movement, and his personal life. Letters from friends and family include many from Hans and Maria Hofmann. Letters by Bultman are mostly to family; also found are a few drafts and copies of business and personal letters. Writings and notes are by and about Bultman. Notebooks/sketchbooks (39 volumes) include autobiographical writings, notes on dreams and thoughts while in psychoanalysis, many sketches and some completed drawings. Subject files reflect Bultman's professional activities, interests, and relationships. Extensive printed material concerns Bultman's activities and exhibitions; also included are his published writings. Most photographs are of artwork, Bultman, his family and friends. Also found are biographical materials, 4 diaries, 6 interviews with Fritz Bultman and Jeanne Bultman, and a small amount of artwork.
Biographical materials include school records and notice of Bultman's army classification.
Most letters are addressed to Fritz Bultman and his parents. Fritz's education in Munich and studying with Hans Hofmann is well-documented. Many letters are from Miz Hofmann and Hans Hofmann. Also found are a smaller number of letters from museums, galleries, universities, and arts organizations. The surviving letters by Bultman are mainly to his family. Most were written when he was a student in Munich or traveling in Europe. There are some drafts and copies of letters concerning professional activities, arrangements for lectures, exhibitions, and Cynthia Goodman's editing "Form and Color in the Creative Process: The Painter's Primer" by Hans Hofmann.
Most interviews focus on Bultman's career. An interview with Jeanne and Fritz Bultman is about John Graham, and one of the interviews with Jeanne Bultman concerns Hans Hofmann.
Bultman's writings and notes include articles, lectures and talks about Hans Hofman, lectures about his own work, and a book review. Among the writings about Bultman are articles, a catalog essay and exhibition review.
Notebooks/sketchbooks (39 volumes) contain a variety of writings and notes, including some that are autobiographical, along with sketches and several finished drawings. Some volumes consist of writings and notes with a few sketches and doodles while others are mainly sketchbooks containing a few stray notes and brief writings; many contain approximately the same amount of text and drawings.
Diaries (4 volumes) contain entries about his work, professional and personal activities. One volume is a record of his October 1978 trip to Istanbul.
Subject files contain varying combinations of correspondence, photographs, printed material, and manuscripts. The most extensive file relates to Hans Hofmann and includes copies of writings by him. Other files of note concern Joseph Cornell, the exhibitions "Forum '49" and "Forum '49 Revisited," Weldon Kees, Tony Smith, and Donald Windham.
The largest series, printed material, consists of exhibition catalogs, announcements, reviews, articles and clippings about or mentioning Bultman.
Noteworthy among the small amount of artwork by Bultman is an early print; also found are loose drawings and paintings on paper.
Photographs of artwork document the full range of Bultman's production --paintings, sculpture, drawings, collage, stained glass, interior design and decoration. Also found are a few photographs of works by other artists. Photographs of Fritz Bultman include many by Renate Ponsold. Other indentified individuals include parents Fred and Pauline Bultman, sister Muriel Bultman, childhood nurse Katie Belle, son Johann Bultman, Sherman Drexler, Hans Hofmann, Miz Hofmann, Miss Katsura, Lee Krasner, Annalee Newman, Barnett Newman, Alfonso Ossorio, Jeanne Reynal, Thomas Sills, Jack Tworkov, and Wally Tworkov. A group portrait of the artists of Long Point Gallery includes: Varujan Boghosian, Fritz Bultman, Carmen Cicero, Sideo Fromboluti, Budd Hopkins, Rick Klauber, Lee Manso, Sidney Simon, Robert Motherwell, Judith Rothschild, Nora Speyer, and Tony Vevers. Also found in this series are photographs of Bultman exhibition installations and views of miscellaneous places.
Biographical/Historical note
Fritz Bultman (1919-1985), a New York School painter and sculptor who lived and worked in Provincetown, Massachusetts and New York City, was also a collagist, stained glass artist, and educator.
Anthony Fred Bultman, III --always known as Fritz --was from a prominent and cultured New Orleans family. He began studying art as a boy and one of his teachers was Morris Graves, a family friend. His last 2 years of high school were spent at the Munich Preparatory School, boarding with Mrs. Hans Hofmann whose husband was working in New York for an extended period. Bultman attended the New Bauhaus in Chicago before studying for three years with Hans Hofmann in New York City and Provincetown, Massachusetts. As well as being a major influence on Bultman's development as a painter, Hofmann became a life-long friend.
Fritz Bultman met dancer and model Jeanne Lawson (1918-2008), when she was posing in Hofmann's studio during the summer of 1941. They married in 1943 and the following year bought a house in Provincetown. In 1945, Bultman built a studio designed by a friend from the New Bauhaus, sculptor and architectural designer Tony Smith, who also helped with its construction.
His first solo exhibition was held in 1947 at the Hugo Gallery, New York; others followed in 1950, again at Hugo Gallery and at Kootz Gallery, New York. After receiving an Italian Government Grant for Exchange Fellowship, Bultman spent 1950-1951 in Florence, Italy, where he learned the process of casting and began making metal sculpture. In 1952 the Bultmans moved to New York City. Depressed and beset by anxiety, Bultman began Freudian psychoanalysis, and between 1952 and 1956 produced very little artwork.
In 1958 Bultman resumed exhibiting and continued to show regularly for the remainder of his life. He enjoyed solo exhibitions in New York City, Paris, New Orleans, North Carolina, Provincetown, and other venues. Between 1958 and 1963 Bultman taught painting at Hunter College and was an instructor in design and painting at Pratt Institute. Bultman spent 1964-1965 in Paris on a Fulbright Grant painting and sculpting, studying European methods of bronze casting, and meeting French artists. Bultman maintained his reputation as a highly regarded art instructor and in later years was a sought after guest lecturer at a various colleges. While artist-in-residence at Kalamazoo College, Michigan in 1981, he designed and produced a stained glass mural with technical assistance from his wife, Jeanne Bultman, a skilled artisan.
Fritz Bultman died of cancer in Provincetown, Massachusetts, in 1985.
Related Archival Materials note
An oral history interview with Fritz Bultman, 1986 January 6, was conducted by Irving Sandler for the Archives of American Art (available on microfilm reel 3196).
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment. Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
Boghosian, Varujan; Bultman, Jeanne; Cicero, Carmen, 1926-; Cornell, Joseph; Drexler, Sherman; Fromboluti, Sideo, 1921-; Graham, John, 1887-1961; Hofmann, Hans, 1880-1966; Hofmann, Maria, 1885-1963; Hopkins, Budd, 1931-; Kees, Weldon, 1914-1955; Krasner, Lee, 1908-; Manso, Leo; Motherwell, Robert; Newman, Annette; Newman, Barnett, 1905-1970; Ossorio, Alfonso, 1916-; Ponsold, Renate; Reynal, Jeanne, 1903-; Rothschild, Judith; Sills, Thomas, 1914-; Simon, Sidney, 1917-1997; Smith, Tony, 1912-1980; Speyer, Nora; Tworkov, Jack; Vevers, Tony; Windham, Donald; Abstract expressionism; Diaries; Drawings; Interviews; New York school of art; Painters--New York (State)--New York; Painting, Modern--20th century--New York (State)--New York; Paintings; Photographs; Sculptors--New York (State)--New York; Sketchbooks; Sketches
- Biographical Materials, 1928-2003; Series 1; 0.1 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical notes include a list of exhibitions, 1947-2003. School records include report cards from Isidore Newman School, New Orleans, the first issue of "Junior Year in Munich 1935-36 News Letter" featuring "October Diary" (Bultman did not contribute an entry), and his student card from The Munich Preparatory School for the 1936/37 school year.
  Arrangement note
  Additional school records from the period when Bultman studied in Munich are found enclosed with letters (Series 2).
  - Army Classification, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical Notes, circa 1960s-2003 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Obituaries, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - School Records, 1928-1937 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Letters, 1930-1995; Series 2; 0.4 Linear feet Box 1
  Most incoming letters are addressed to Fritz Bultman or family members. Earlier letters concern Fritz's education in Munich, enrollment at the New Bauhaus, and studies with Hans Hofmann in New York and Provincetown, Massachusetts. Many letters are from Miz Hofmann (in German, some with translations) and from Hans Hofmann offering advice and encouragement; after the outbreak of World War II, they sought Bultman's help to obtain documents necessary for Mrs. Hofmann to join her husband in the United States. As Bultman's career progressed, incoming letters concerned exhibitions, sales, and invitations to lecture or serve as a visiting professor. In addition to brief notes and messages from Jeanne Bultman to Fritz, mostly of a routine nature, there are frequent, lengthy letters sent while traveling in Europe. Letters post-dating Bultman's death concern exhibitions, loans, and sales.
  The majority of letters by Bultman are to his family; a large portion were written when he was a student. Some drafts and copies of letters by Bultman concern professional activities such as arrangements for lectures, exhibitions, and Cynthia Goodman's editing of "Form and Color in the Creative Process: The Painter's Primer" by Hans Hofmann.
  Incoming and outgoing letters are filed together and arranged by year. Additional letters are included among the subject files (Series 7).
  - Letters, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letters from Miz Hofmann, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letters, 1930-1995 (Box 1, Folder 7-27)
- Interviews, circa 1968-1998; Series 3; 0.4 Linear feet Box 1
  Interviews are with Fritz Bultman (1 sound cassette and 2 transcripts), Jeanne and Fritz Bultman together (1 videocassette: U-matic), and Jean Bultman (2 transcripts). Most are about Bultman's career; the undated interview with Bultman probably is incomplete. One interview with Fritz Bultman concerns John Graham and one with Jeanne Bultman focuses on Hans Hofmann.
  - Fritz Bultman Interview conducted by Unidentified Interviewer, undated; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Fritz Bultman Interview conducted by Irving Sandler (1968 January 5), transcript, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - "An Interview with Fritz Bultman about John Graham" conducted by Ellen Landau (1979 February 27 and 1979 April 31), transcript, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Jeanne and Fritz Bultman interviewed on "Accent," WKOZ-TV (1985 February 8), 1 Videocassettes (U-matic) (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Jeanne Bultman Interview about Hans Hofmann conducted by Tina Dickey (1998 October 18), transcript, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Jeanne Bultman Interview conducted by Elizabeth Simonson and Jensene Payne (1997 December 12), transcript, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Writings and Notes, 1935-circa 1980s; Series 4; 0.8 Linear feet Boxes 1-2
  The majority of Bultman's writings are texts or notes on a variety of topics for lectures and talks presented at universities and professional conferences. Also found are articles, a book review, and catalog essay. Writings about Bultman include a variety of articles, a review, and "Quotes re: Fritz Bultman and His Work," extracted from published sources and letters, 1950-1983. Miscellaneous writings are shorter pieces and unidentified fragments. Included is a poem by L.G. dedicated to Bultman.
  - By Bultman (Box 1)
    - Articles, Lectures and Talks about Hans Hofmann, undated (Box 1, Folder 34-35)
    - Book Review, circa 1961 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Exhibition Catalog Essay (with April Kingsley), "Cape Cod as an Art Colony," Heritage Museum, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Extracts from Unpublished Notebooks and Lectures, undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Lectures and Talks - "The Thing, The Veiled Scene, and The Wall", 1957 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Lectures and Talks - The Direct Vision and Conditioned Vision in Looking at Art, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Lectures and Talks - "Nature, Naturalism, and the Dream", 1962 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Lectures and Talks -- "Homage to St. Luke," An Address for the 20th Arts Festival, The Woman's College of the University of North Carolina Greensboro", 1963 (Box 1, Folder 42-44)
    - Lectures and Talks - "The Chicago Talk", 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Lectures and Talks -- Fine Arts Work Center, Provincetown, 1968-1972 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Lectures and Talks -- "Why I Draw from the Figure", 1969-1981 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Lectures and Talks -- "About My Drawings", circa 1972 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Lectures and Talks -- "Monumental Sculpture and Monumental Space," 9th International Sculpture Conference, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Lectures and Talks -- Hofmann Lecture at Hirshhorn Museum, 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Lectures and Talks -- Western Carolina University, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Lectures and Talks -- "Hofmann and Albers as Master Teachers," College Art Association Panel, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Lectures and Talks -- "Lecture on Hans Hofmann for Parsons School of Design 1980", 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Lectures and Talks -- Kalamazoo College, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Miscellaneous Writings, undated; 1950s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 7-9)
    - Notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Statements, 1964-1979 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - About Bultman (Box 2)
    - Ewald, Bethany. Article for New Orleans Magazine, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Friedman, B. H. "'The Irascibles': A Split Second in Art History", 1978 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Friedman, Sanford. "The Glad Tidings of Fritz Bultman", 1976 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Kingsley, April. "Fritz Bultman", undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Lawlor, Robert. From Notebooks of Fritz Bultman, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Shuebrook, Ron. "Fritz Bultman Remembered", undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Stephens, Michael. "The Drawings of Fritz Bultman", undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Multiple Authors. Quotes re: Fritz Bultman and His Work (1950-1983), undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Unsigned. Review, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
    - Bonnard, Pierre. "A Bouquet of Roses", circa 1955-circa 1985 (Box 2, Folder 21)
      transcribed by Angele Lamotte in 1943 and copied later by Bultman
    - Gilmore, Louis. Poems, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
      dedicated to Bultman
    - Goulish, Matthew and Barbara Guest. Poems, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Notebooks/Sketchbooks, 1937-circa 1979; Series 5; 0.7 Linear feet Boxes 2-3, 11
  Notebooks/sketchbooks (39 volumes) contain a variety of writings and notes (including some that are autobiographical), along with sketches and several finished drawings. Some volumes consist of writings and notes with a few sketches and doodles while others are mainly sketchbooks containing a few stray notes and brief writings; many contain approximately the same amount of text and drawings. Included are a volume titled "Venice" (1937), "New Bauhaus" from his year in Chicago (1937-1938), "N.Y.C." (circa 1938), and 3 volumes that focus on his psychoanalysis (1952-1953).
  This series is arranged chronologically.
  - Volume 1, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Volume 2, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Volume 3, "Venice", circa 1937 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Volume 5, "New Bauhaus", 1937-1938 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Volume 4, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Volume 6, "NYC", circa 1938 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Volume 7, 1938-1939 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Volume 8, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Volume 9, 1940-1941 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Volume 10, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Volume 11, 1943-1944 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Volume 12, circa 1944-circa 1949 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Volume 13, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Volume 14, circa 1946-circa 1948 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Volume 15, circa 1947 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Volume 16, circa 1947-1949 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Volume 17, 1947-1948 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Volume 18, 1949-1950 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    includes negatives
  - Volume 19, 1950-circa 1953 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Volume 20, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Volume 21, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Volume 22, "Personal - Dreams", 1952 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Volume 23, "Personal - Dreams - In Treatment", 1952-1953 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Volume 24, "Dreams - Personal - During Treatment", 1953 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Volume 25, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Volume 26, 1959-1960 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Volume 27, circa 1960s (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Volume 28, 1960-1962; Oversized volume 28 housed in Box 11 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Volume 29, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Volume 30, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Volume 31, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Volume 32, "Drawings and Personal", 1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Volume 33, 1967-1968 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Volume 34, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Volume 35, circa 1970-circa 1974 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Volume 36, 1970-1974 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Volume 37, 1973-1984 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Volume 38, circa 1973-circa 1977 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Volume 39, circa 1977-circa 1979 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Loose Pages from Unidentified Volumes, undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Oversized Volume 28 from Box 3 Folder 5, 1960-1962 (Box 11)
- Diaries, 1977-1979; Series 6; 0.3 Linear feet Box 3
  Entries, usually a full page, are about professional and personal activities. Volumes 1 and 2 contain almost daily entries with a few brief gaps; volume 4 includes longer periods without entries. Volume 3 was written while on a trip to Istanbul in October 1978.
  Volumes are arranged chronologically.
  - Volume 1, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Volumes 2 and 3, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Volume 4, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Subject Files, 1942-2010; Series 7; 2.3 Linear feet Boxes 3-5, 11
  Subject files reflect some of Bultman's activities, interests, and relationships. Individual files in this series may contain a wide variety of record types or consist simply of correspondence with or about an individual or institution.
  The most thoroughly documented subject is Hans Hofmann. Printed materials include articles about Hofmann, a brochure of the Hans Hofmann School of Fine Arts, exhibition notices and catalogs. Among the writings by Hofmann are: an article, "Plastic Creation;" his essay, "Form and Color in the Creative Process: The Painter's Primer" (edited by Cynthia Goodman, translated by Georgina Huck); and a book, The Search for the Real (edited by Sarah T. Weeks and Bartlett H. Hayes, Jr.); as well as lectures and talks.
  Joseph Cornell documentation includes letters referring to Napoleonic Parakeet, a Cornell box owned by the Bultmans; also found are postcards and further correspondence. Printed material, mostly about exhibitions, includes a notice about Cornell's memorial service.
  "Forum '49" and "Forum '49 Revisited" includes photographs of the 1949 installation and the participating artists --Fritz Bultman, Peter Busa, Kenneth Campbell, Minna Citron, Morris Davidson, Lillian Drake, Perle Fine, William Freed, Howard Gibbs, Kahlil Gibran, Adolph Gottlieb, John Grillo, Weldon Kees, Karl Knaths, Lawrence and Mrs. Kupferman, Blanche Lazzell, Boris Margo, George McNeil, F. Pfeiffer, and Judith Rothschild.
  Found in the Weldon Kees file are requests for information about Kees, Bultman's notes about their friendship, along with a few letters from Kees and manuscripts of articles about him. The file concerning the Provincetown History Preservation Project contains many original letters of Fritz and Jeanne Bultman, a few photographs, and other items that Mrs. Bultman thought might be of interest to the project. Documentation of friendships with Tony Smith and Donald Windham includes a substantial number of letters. The Windham file also includes writings and there is a book cover Bultman designed for him.
  Subject files are alphabetized by title.
  - 96th Street Playground Association Project, 1980; Oversized material housed in Box 11 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - American Abstract Artists, 1949-1951 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Art, 1997-1998 (Box 3, Folder 23-24)
  - Art, 1999-2003 (Box 4, Folder 1-3)
  - The Bultman Mortuary Service, Inc., 1975-1981; undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
    The funeral home was also referred to as House of Bultman and there is a subject file with that title.
  - College Art Association (1980 January) -- Panel, "Hofmann and Albers as Master Teachers", 1979-1980 (Box 4, Folder 5)